Guide to the Ed Wilkinson Collection ARS.0092
Archive of Recorded Sound
Ed Wilkinson Collection
1934-1953
ARS.0092
Wilkinson, Ed
4 boxes: 71 tapes (sixty 10.5" reels; eleven 7" reels)
Archive of Recorded Sound
The Ed Wilkinson Collection consists of classical and opera performance broadcasts of the 1930s and 40s on open reel tape, the majority of which from the Standard Symphony Hour series.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The Ed Wilkinson Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by Ed Wilkinson in 1983.
Scope and Contents
The Ed Wilkinson Collection consists of seventy-two audiotape copies of radio programs of classical music and opera from 1934 to 1953. The collection, which was transferred by Wilkinson to tape in 1983, features the Standard Symphony Hour series (also known as the Standard Hour), the Metropolitan Opera, and the San Francisco Symphony and Opera. Various sources were used to assemble the programs. Each tape box has extensive technical and content notes.
Collector Ed Wilkinson was associated with the Western Sound Archive, a nonprofit archive founded by Nate Brown in Los Osos, California. Both Brown and Wilkinson share a long association with the Archive of Recorded Sound, and have donated many rare recordings. At one point, the Western Sound Archive was considered the source of nearly all circulating Standard Hour broadcasts. These Standard Hour programs comprise the majority of the Wilkinson collection. Many were dubbed from original network transcription discs once owned by Adrian Michaelis, program manager for the series. Other sources for the program are noted as NBC linechecks, Photo And Sound airchecks, and from other tapes. The Archive also holds many of the original NBC discs for Standard Hour in its transcription collection.
Orchestras include the Standard Symphony Orchestra, Los Angeles Philharmonic, and San Francisco Symphony Orchestra. Vocal soloists include Lotte Lehmann, Blanche Thebom, Lily Pons, Maggie Teyte, Dusolina Giannini, Jussi Bjoerling, and Bidu Sayao. Among the instrumental soloists are Joseph Szigeti, Robert Casadesus, Isaac Stern, and Artur Schnabel. The collection also contains some unusual performances by Yehudi Menuhin, such as a Stage Door Canteen broadcast from 1943 and a Town Hall concert with Wanda Landowska from 1944.
Indexing Terms
Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.). Orchestra.; Standard Hour Program (Radio program).; Radio programs
- 1. Standard Hour broadcasts, 48 10.5" open reel tapes (95 programs)
  - 721, 1941-02-27 (Audio 1, Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra
  - 722, 1941-03-06 (Audio 1, Reel 1)
    Svedrofsky, Standard Symphony Orchestra of Los Angeles
  - 723, 1941-03-13 (Audio 1, Reel 2)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony.
  - 724, 1941-03-20 (Audio 1, Reel 2)
    Svedrofsky, Standard Symphony Orchestra of Los Angeles, Lloyd Browning
  - 739, 1941-07-03 (Audio 1, Reel 3)
    Monteux, Standard Symphony Orchestra of San Francisco
  - 742, 1941-07-24 (Audio 1, Reel 4)
    Monteux, Standard Symphony Orchestra of San Francisco, Robert Brereton
  - 865, 1943-11-28 (Audio 1, Reel 5)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Lee Sweetland
  - 866, 1943-12-05 (Audio 1, Reel 5)
  - 867, 1943-12-12 (Audio 1, Reel 6)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Lotte Lehmann
  - 868, 1943-12-19 (Audio 1, Reel 6)
    San Francisco Bank Chorus, Warren Otey
  - 871, 1944-01-09 (Audio 1, Reel 7)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Dusolina Giannini
  - 872, 1944-01-16 (Audio 1, Reel 7)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Dusolina Giannini, Carl Fuerstner
  - 873, 1944-01-23 (Audio 1, Reel 8)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Wendell Otey
  - 874, 1944-01-30 (Audio 1, Reel 8)
    Merola, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Dusolina Giannini
  - 917, 1944-11-26 (Audio 1, Reel 9)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra
  - 918, 1944-12-03 (Audio 1, Reel 9)
  - 920, 1944-12-17 (Audio 1, Reel 10)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Maxim Shapiro
  - 925, 1945-01-21 (Audio 1, Reel 11)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Joseph Szigeti
  - 926 (Audio 1, Reel 11)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Don Cossack Chorus, dir. Serge Jaroff
  - 967, 1945-11-11 (Audio 1, Reel 12)
    Merola, San Francisco Opera
  - 968, 1945-11-18 (Audio 1, Reel 12)
  - 976, 1946-01-13 (Audio 1, Reel 13)
    Alfred Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Artur Schnabel
  - 981, 1946-02-17 (Audio 1, Reel 14)
    Alfred Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Isaac Stern
  - 982, 1946-02-24 (Audio 1, Reel 14)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Opera, Boris Blinder
  - 985, 1946-03-17 (Audio 1, Reel 15)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Witold Malcuzynski
  - 986, 1946-03-24 (Audio 1, Reel 15)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Lev Shorr
  - 987, 1946-03-31 (Audio 1, Reel 16)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Maxim Schapiro
  - 988, 1946-04-07 (Audio 1, Reel 16)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Jospeh Szigeti
  - 1023, 1946-12-08 (Audio 1, Reel 17)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Wanda Krasoff
  - 1024 (Audio 1, Reel 17)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Jørgen Nielsen
  - 1033, 1947-02-16 (Audio 1, Reel 18)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Mischa Elman
  - 1034, 1947-02-23 (Audio 1, Reel 18)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Maggie Teyte
  - 1035, 1947-03-02 (Audio 1, Reel 19)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Robert Casadesus
  - 1036, 1947-03-09 (Audio 1, Reel 19)
    Charles Munch, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Gilles Guilbert
  - 1075, 1947-12-07 (Audio 1, Reel 20)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Naoum Blinder, Boris Blinder
  - 1076, 1947-12-14 (Audio 1, Reel 20)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Rose Bampton, Max Lichtegg
  - 1087, 1948-02-29 (Audio 1, Reel 21)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Dorothy Warenskjold
  - 1088, 1948-03-07 (Audio 1, Reel 21)
  - 1089 (Audio 1, Reel 22)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic
  - 1090, 1948-03-21 (Audio 1, Reel 22)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Merrill Remington, Dorothy Warenskjold
  - 1091, 1948-03-28 (Audio 2, Reel 1)
  - 1092, 1948-03-04 (Audio 2, Reel 1)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Robert Brereton
  - 1093, 1948-04-11 (Audio 2, Reel 2)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Jennie Tourel
  - 1094, 1948-04-18 (Audio 2, Reel 2)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Mario Berini
  - 1131, 1949-01-02 (Audio 2, Reel 3)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Stanley Noonan
  - 1132, 1949-01-09 (Audio 2, Reel 3)
    Monteaux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Nan Merriman
  - 1153, 1949-06-05 (Audio 4, Reel 12)
    Barnett, Standard Symphony Of Los Angeles, Marina Koshetz
  - 1154, 1949-06-12 (Audio 4, Reel 12)
    Walter, Standard Symphony Of California, Leon Fleisher
  - 1155, 1949-06-19 (Audio 2, Reel 4)
    Walter, Standard Symphony Orchestra of Los Angeles
  - 1156, 1949-06-26 (Audio 2, Reel 4)
    Abravanel, Standard Symphony Orchestra of Los Angeles, Dorothy Warenskjold, Joseph Schuster
  - 1173, 1949-10-23 (Audio 2, Reel 5)
    Merola, San Francisco Opera, Jussi Björling, Annalisa Björling
  - 1222, 1950-10-01 (Audio 2, Reel 5)
    Merola, San Francisco Opera, Bidú Sayão, Giuseppe di Stefano
  - 1179, 1949-12-04 (Audio 2, Reel 6)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Lili Kraus
  - 1180, 1949-12-11 (Audio 2, Reel 6)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Rudolf Firkusny
  - 1187, 1950-01-29 (Audio 2, Reel 7)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Vivian Della Chiesa
  - 1188, 1950-02-05 (Audio 2, Reel 7)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Caroll Glenn
  - 1191, 1950-02-26 (Audio 2, Reel 8)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Jesus Maria San Roma
  - 1192, 1950-03-05 (Audio 2, Reel 8)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Jennie Tourel
  - 1193, 1950-03-12 (Audio 2, Reel 9)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, David Lloyd
  - 1194, 1950-03-19 (Audio 2, Reel 9)
  - 1197, 1950-04-09 (Audio 2, Reel 10)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Isaac Stern
  - 1198, 1950-04-16 (Audio 2, Reel 10)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Dorothy Sarnoff
  - 1221 (Audio 2, Reel 11)
    Merola, San Francisco Opera, Lily Pons, Eugene Conley
  - 1222, 1950-10-01 (Audio 2, Reel 11)
  - 1231, 1950-12-03 (Audio 2, Reel 12)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Lyell Barbour
  - 1232, 1950-12-10 (Audio 2, Reel 12)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Naoum Blinder, Boris Blinder
  - 1233, 1950-12-17 (Audio 2, Reel 13)
    Stravinsky, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra
  - 1234, 1950-12-24 (Audio 2, Reel 13)
    Barnett, Standard Symphony Orchestra of Los Angeles, Roger Wagner Chorale
  - 1235, 1950-12-31 (Audio 2, Reel 14)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Yehudi Menhin
  - 1236, 1951-01-07 (Audio 2, Reel 14)
  - 1243, 1951-02-25 (Audio 2, Reel 15)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Ruggiero Ricci
  - 1244, 1951-03-04 (Audio 2, Reel 15)
  - 1271, 1952-01-27 (Audio 2, Reel 16)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Virginia Haskins
  - 1292, 1952-02-03 (Audio 2, Reel 16)
  - 1247, 1951-03-25 (Audio 2, Reel 17)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Dorothy Warenskjold
  - 1248, 1951-04-01 (Audio 2, Reel 17)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Paulena Carter
  - 1285, 1951-12-16 (Audio 2, Reel 18)
  - 1286, 1951-12-23 (Audio 2, Reel 18)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Aldo Ciccolini
  - 1287, 1951-12-30 (Audio 2, Reel 19)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Yehudi Menuhin
  - 1288, 1952-01-06 (Audio 2, Reel 19)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Guiomar Novaes
  - 1289, 1952-01-13 (Audio 2, Reel 20)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Tossy Spivakovsky
  - 1290, 1952-01-20 (Audio 2, Reel 20)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, David Frisina
  - 1295, 1952-02-24 (Audio 2, Reel 21)
    Sample, Portland Symphony Orchestra, Paulena Carter
  - 1296, 1952-03-02 (Audio 2, Reel 21)
  - 1297, 1952-03-09 (Audio 2, Reel 22)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Claramae Turner
  - 1298, 1952-03-16; folders (Audio 2, Reel 22)
    Wallenstein, Los Angeles Philharmonic, Dorothy Dow
  - 1300, 1952-03-30 (Audio 3, Reel 1)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Caesar Curzi
  - 1301, 1952-04-06 (Audio 3, Reel 2)
    Monteux, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Joseph Spivakovsky
  - 1302, 1952-04-13 (Audio 3, Reel 2)
  - 1331, 1952-11-02 (Audio 3, Reel 3)
    Merola, San Francisco Opera, Blanche Thebom, Robert Weede
  - 1332, 1952-11-09 (Audio 3, Reel 3)
    Sample, Portland Symphony Orchestra, Zahava Edelsack
  - 1343, 1953-01-25 (Audio 3, Reel 4)
    Wallenstein, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Arthur Grumiaux
  - 1344, 1953-02-01 (Audio 3, Reel 4)
    De Sabata, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, Francis Yeend
  - [no number], 1953-09-27 (Audio 3, Reel 5)
    Serafin, San Francisco Opera Orchestra
  - [no number], 1943-09-19 (Audio 3, Reel 5)
    Merola, San Francisco Opera Orchestra
- 2. other broadcasts
  - Donizetti. L'Elisir d'amore. Antonicelli, Metropolitan Opera, 1949-12-24; 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 4, Reel 1, Reel 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes intermission programs. NBC San Francisco linechecks, from collection of Adrian Michaelis. Transferred 1983.
  - Gounod. Romeo and Juliet. Metropolitan Opera, 1947-02-01; 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 4, Reel 5, Reel 6)
  - Hollywood Bowl, 1947-07-27; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3, Reel 12)
    Scope And Contents
    Symphony conducted by Vladimir Golschmann. Florence Quartararo, soprano. From Standard Hour linechecks and AFRS discs from ARS Collection.
  - Massenet. Manon. Wilfred Pelletier, Metropolitan Opera, 1940-01-13; 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 4, Reel 10, Reel 11)
    From NBC lacquers, dubbed 1960, redubbed 1983.
  - Yehudi Menuhin Private Recordings (notes enclosed), 1941-1953; 3 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3, Reel 13-15)
    includes Town Hall concert with Wanda Landowska Dec. 20, 1944; Stage Door Canteen March 3, 1943; interviews, etc.
    Menuhin, Yehudi, 1916-1999
  - Puccini. Madame Butterfly. Gennaro Papi, San Francisco Opera, 1939-11-03; 1 7" open reel tapes (Audio 4, Reel 7)
    Act III not recorded. From NBC audition in Girard/Farwig collection, dubbed by Wilkinson 1983.
  - Rossini. Il Barbiere di Siviglia. Gennaro Pap, Metropolitan Opera, 1941-03-01; 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 4, Reel 8, Reel 9)
    From NBC linecheck in Girard/Farwig collection, dubbed by Wilkinson 1983.
  - Saint-Saens. Samson and Delilah. Abravanel, Metropolitan Opera 1936-12-26 (reel 4 also contains Act 3 of Lohengrin, 1934-03-24), 1934-1936; 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 4, Reel 3, Reel 4)
    Scope aned Contents
    From NBC linechecks, dubbed 1960, pitched, edited and redubbed by Wilkinson 1982.
  - Strauss. Der Rosenkavalier. Reiner, Metropolitan Opera (1949), 1949-12-03; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3, Reel 11)
  - Strauss. Der Rosenkavalier. Reiner, Metropolitan Opera (1951), 1951-02-24; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3, Reel 9, Reel 10)
    Act I on Reel 9, acts II and III on Reel 10. "Present tape is a compound of a tape dub (majority of music) and linechecks/acetates, collection of A. Michaelis (intermissions, announcements, and two brief segments in Act I). Sound is good."
  - Wagner. Die Meistersinger. Reiner, Metropolitan Opera, 1953-01-10; 2 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 3, Reel 8, Reel 9)
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    Acts I and II on Reel 8. Act III on Reel 9. "Present tape is a composite of fair-sounding dub of highlights and a poorish AM dub of the complete performance, edited 1980 by E. Wilkinson. This is the only dub currently in circulation (April 1983)."
  - Wagner. Lohengrin. Bodansky, Metropolitan Opera, Melchior (Box 3 contains Acts 1 and 2, Box 4 contains Act 3), 1934-03-24; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 4, Reel 4, Audio 3, Reel 6)
  - Wagner. Die Walküre. McArthur, San Francisco Opera, Melchior, Flagstad (Portion of Act 2), 1939-10-24; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3, Reel 7)
  - Wagner. Tristan und Isolde. McArthur, San Francisco Opera, Melchior, Flagstad (Portion of Act 1), 1939-10-20; 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 3, Reel 7)